Finding Aid for School of Dentistry (University of Michigan) Publications 1875-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Dentistry (University of Michigan) Publications 1875-2011
University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.
The collection contains annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins and college catalogs, directories, histories, lectures, manuals, and newsletters such as the Alumni Bulletin, Alumni News, Dentalum, The Michigan Dental Explorer, Newsline and The Staff and Student Newsletter. Also included are publications from departments and other sub-units of the school, programs from the Honors Convocation, reports, and the student yearbook
0345 Bimu C121 2
7.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 764 )
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The School of Dentistry (University of Michigan) Publications are open for research without restriction.
See the historic sketch in the finding aid for School of Dentistry (University of Michigan) finding aid.
The Publications of the School of Dentistry contains annual reports, brochures and pamphlets, bulletins and college catalogs, directories, histories, lectures, manuals, and newsletters such as the Alumni Bulletin, Alumni News, Dentalum, The Michigan Dental Explorer, Newsline and The Staff and Student Newsletter. Also includes publications of departments and other sub-units of the school, programs from the Honors Convocation, reports and the student yearbook. The Publications are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications. Some publications (or their successors) may no longer be available in print but are available on the school s website.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Community Dentistry.; University of Michigan. Dental Society.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Educational Resources.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Endodontics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Occlusion.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Operative Dentistry.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Oral Biology.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Oral Diagnosis.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Oral Surgery.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Orthodontics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Periodontics.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Dental Society.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Educational Resources.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Endodontics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Occlusion.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Operative Dentistry.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Oral Biology.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Oral Diagnosis.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry. Dept. of Oral Surgery.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Orthodontics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Periodontics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Community Dentistry.
Genre/Form:
Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Catalogs, College.; Directories.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Programs.
- Unit Publications
  Unit Publications include bulletins, staff directories, runs of the newsletters Alumni News, and Alumni Bulletin, whose title changed to DentalUM in 1990. The histories included in this record group are about the University of Michigan School of Dentistry, but were produced by other sources with the exception of A Compilation of Historical Data. Additionally, two of these histories are written in Spanish. Also included are annual reports for the years 1920-1978 and Yearbooks for the years 1966-1985.
  - Annual Reports 1920-1978, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - 1936-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1996 (Box 1)
    - 2000-2003 (Box 1)
    - Undated (Box 1)
    - Dental Scholars (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - 1875-1995, 25 folders (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995, 1997-2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Curriculum in Oral/Dental Hygiene 1928-1944 (Box 2)
    - Postgraduate Courses in Dentistry 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - Continuing Education 1999-2000, 2002-2005 (Box 2)
    - Degree Requirements 2006, 2009, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Dietary Program for the Control of Denial Carries 1951 (Box 2)
  - Directories
    - Staff Directory 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Student Directory 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - Histories
    - A Compilation of Historical Data, Referring to the Dental Department of the University of Michigan, 1902 (Box 2)
    - Dentista Conservadora en la Escuela Dental de Michigan, 1944 (Box 2)
    - History of College of Dental Surgery, University of Michigan, 1875-1925 (Box 2)
    - Universidad de Michigan Escuela de Odontologia, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Lectures
    - Lectures of Dental Materia Medica and Therapeutics, 1901-1902 (Box 3)
  - Manuals
    - How to Take the Bite Out of Dental School: Student Handbook, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Laboratory Projects in Applied Dental Physics, 1954 (Box 3)
    - Report Writing in Dentistry: A Teaching Outline, 1948-1959 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - Alumni Bulletin, 1936-1980, 12 folders (Box 3)
    - Alumni E-Newsletter, 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - Alumni News, 1978-1990, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Dental Alumni News, 1963-1964, 1967 (Box 3)
    - DentalUM
      - 1990-2002, 10 folders (Box 3)
      - 2002-2014, 11 folders (Box 4)
      - The Michigan Dental Explorer, 1975-1981, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Newsline, 1981-1991, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - Staff and Student Newsletter, 1962-1965 (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - 125th Anniversary Celebration and Facilities Dedication 2000 (Box 4)
  - Programs (cont.)
    - Annual Homecoming 1936-1939 (Box 4)
    - Commencement Exercises 1895 (Box 4)
    - Commencement Programs 1990, 1992-1995, 2006, 2007, 2009-2010 (Box 4)
    - Dedication of Dental Building 1909 (Box 4)
    - Honors Convocation 1923-1968, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Senior Class Day 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - Reports
    - Dental Building, Section 1--Program Statement, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Research in the School of Dentistry 1967-1976 (Box 4)
  - Research Table Clinic Day 2001, 2004-2006 (Box 5)
  - Symposiums
    - Implementation of Contemporary Biology in Dental Curriculum, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Salivary Glands and Their Secretion, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Workbooks 1920-1921
    - Notes on General Pathology (Box 5)
    - Pyorrhea Alveolaria (Box 5)
    - No title given (animal dentistry) (Box 5)
  - Workshops
    - Future Requirements of Dental Manpower, 1962 (Box 5)
    - International Prosthodontic Workshop, 1972 (Box 5)
    - The Relative Efficiency of Methods of Caries Prevention in Dental Public Health, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Yearbooks
    - 1966-1967, 1969-1970, 1972-1976, 9 folders (Box 5)
    - 1976-1980, 1982-1985, 8 folders (Box 6)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  Sub-Unit Publications consist of materials produced by units within the School of Dentistry. These include the Dental Society which produced the newsletter Dental Journal. The Department of Orthodontics publications include manuals and workbooks to accompany classes as well as annual reports and a case analysis of an orthodontic patient. The Development Office publications include brochures and the Honor Roll of Donors and Volunteers. The materials from the W. K. Kellogg Foundation Institute will be found in a separate record group. Other Sub-Units represented include Dental Hygiene, the Department of Educational Resources, the Department of Oral Biology, the Library, and the Postgraduate Division. The publications from these Sub-Units include primarily annual reports and brochures.
  - Alumni Conference Committee
    - Brochures 1964-1975 (Box 6)
  - Complete Denture Department
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 6)
  - Crown and Bridge Department
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 6)
  - Dental Clinic
    - Brochures undated (Box 6)
  - Dental Hygiene
    - Annual Reports 1964-1974 (Box 6)
    - Brochures undated, 1970-1994 (Box 6)
  - Dental Materials Department
    - Annual Reports 1963-1974 (Box 6)
  - Dental Research Institute
    - Brochure undated (Box 6)
  - Dental Society
    - By-Laws
      - Constitution and By-Laws of the Dental Society of the University of Michigan, undated (Box 6)
  - Dental Society (cont.)
    - Newsletters
      - The Dental Journal, 1892-1902, 8 folders (Box 6)
    - Programs
      - Banquet of the Dental Society 1912, 1917 (Box 6)
  - Department of Community Dentistry
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 6)
  - Department of Educational Resources (Box 7)
    - Annual Reports 1969-1974 (Box 7)
    - Manuals
      - Resource Manual for Science Abled: Return on Equity, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Newsletters
      - DER Memo, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Reports
      - Patient Survey of Treatment at the University of Michigan School of Dentistry, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Department of Endodontics
    - Annual Reports 1964-1973 (Box 7)
  - Department of Occlusion
    - Annual Reports 1969-1974 (Box 7)
  - Department of Operative Dentistry
    - Annual Reports 1965-1974 (Box 7)
  - Department of Oral Biology
    - Annual Reports 1963-1974 (Box 7)
    - Proposals
      - Proposal for Graduate Program in Oral Biology, 1982 (Box 7)
  - Department of Oral Diagnosis
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 7)
  - Department of Oral Pathology
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 7)
  - Department of Oral Surgery
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Department of Orthodontics
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 7)
    - Catalog
      - Orthodontics and Pediatric Dentistry, 1999-2000 (Box 7)
    - Histories
      - The History of the University of Michigan Department of Orthodontics Graduate Program (1923-1973), 1973 (Box 7)
    - Manuals
      - Interception of Malocclusion: Orthodontics 748, 1980 (Box 7)
      - Preclinical Orthodontics 621/623, 1981 (Box 7)
    - Reports
      - Case Analysis of an Orthodontic Patient, undated (Box 7)
    - Workbooks
      - Craniofacial Growth, 1977 (Box 7)
  - Department of Periodontics
    - Annual Reports 1962-1974 (Box 7)
    - Brochure 1999 (Box 7)
  - Department of Periodontics (cont.)
    - Manuals
      - Clinic Manual for Periodontics, 2008-2009 (Box 7)
    - Workshops
      - World Workshop in Periodontics, 1966 (Box 7)
  - Development Office (Box 8)
    - Reports
      - Honor Roll of Donors and Volunteers, 1981-2010 2011-ongoing, 15 folders (Box 8)
  - Director of Clinics
    - Annual Reports 1970-1974 (Box 8)
  - Hispanic Dental Association
    - Manual
      - Dental Phrases and Terms in Spanish (Box 8)
  - Library
    - Annual Reports 1956-1960, 1969-1974, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Brochures undated (Box 8)
    - Catalogs
      - Audio-Visual Material 1977 undated (Box 8)
      - Collections Holdings undated (Box 8)
  - Multicultural Affairs Committee
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Day 2000-2001 (Box 8)
    - Newsletter 1998-1999, 2004 (Box 8)
  - Partial Denture Department
    - Annual Reports 1963-1974 (Box 8)
  - Postgraduate Division
    - Manuals
      - Accepted Technics in Children's Dentistry: A Treatment Manual for Postgraduate Extension Courses in Children's Dentistry, 1939 (Box 8)
  - Pre-Clinical Department
    - Annual Reports 1964-1975 (Box 8)
  - Undergraduate Orthodontic Program
    - Reports
      - 1977-78 Five Year Departmental Report 1979 (Box 8)